Oliver Diamond

I am a full-stack (mostly JS: React & Node) developer with a eclectic career. Experienced in approaches that emphasise small composable apps, devops, fast & frequent delivery, clean code, and developer anarchy.

- Current Position: Tes Software Engineer
- Specialisms: Node, React, Mongo, Microservices
- Passions: Linux, Functional, Devops, Spacemacs
- Physics, 2:1, Imperial College London (specialism: Computational Simulations)
- Extensive experience outside programming: Finance, Politics, Media, Communications

Background

I have been programming since I was 13 - building web MMORPGs with friends (*HTML & PHP*) with 1000s of players. At university (2:1 Physics) I spent 2 years programming a bio-ecosystem simulation (*C++*, *OO design*).

Not always a programmer though, I have worked in politics, film production, TV & theatre development, and finance. However, I pushed and built tech solutions in all of these industries from simple web apps (*Node, Python, Ruby*), to finance & news analysis apps (*Java*). I trained and then worked for a top dev bootcamp, focussing on professional full-stack skills and modern methodologies.

Currently I work for Tes (formerly the Times Education Supplement) and (most recently) for HSBC and Makers Academy. I've worked predominantly with the latest Javascript technologies, pushing the following philosphies: **devops, agile, microservices architectures, continuous delivery, constant retrospection and developer anarchy**, whilst always focussing on releasing value to clients.

Skills

Programming:

- JavaScript (Latest ES, Node, React, Express, Dojo, JQuery, RxJS, Selenium) 6+ yrs
- Clojure (Compojure) 1+ yrs
- Java (Android, Spring) 2+ yrs
- Ruby (Rails), Python (Django)
- C++
- CSS, SCSS
- DB (MySQL, PostgreSQL, Mongo)

Delivery/Ops:

- Microservices (Docker, RabbitMQ, Kubernetes, AWS)
- Continuous Delivery (Jenkins, TeamCity, Heroku)
- Version control: Git, RTC
- Linux (Redhat, Debian, Ubuntu)
- Networking (DNS, TCP/IP, HTTPS)
- Spacemacs (Emacs + Vim), Eclipse, Intellij, Android Studio

Methodologies:

- Devops (Fast release cycles)
- Agile (lots of retrospecting)
- Test Driven Development
- Behaviour Driven Development
- Pair Programming
- Microservices Architectures

Other Expertise

Government: I have 8 years experience across Government, public policy, and the digital & creative industries. I became leader of a Minister's Parliamentary Office, and I continue to support a political network that I helped to found.

Finance: Aside from my tech work in HSBC's FX department, I have also worked in a credit-trading hedge fund, a Chinese event-driven brokerage, and a corporate finance boutique (analysing media and tech investments).

Communications: I have worked on public policy campaigns, in political communications, and in film & theatre marketing. I have written articles for national newspapers, press releases for a Minister of State, and organised political conferences.

Work History

Tes Engineering (Oct 2017 - Present) | SOFTWARE ENGINEER

An old company (~100 years), Tes provide teaching resources and solutions. Now that online is the focus of the business, we have recently ungone a massive update to their engineering department.

We're now almost totally microservices, with a JS stack (React, Node, Mongo, funcational design), everything is Dockerised and runs on AWS.

We embrace continuous & fast delivery, agile, devops, open-source, developer anarchy, tiny teams (2-4), remote first, frequent retrospection, hackdays, and a focus on team building and the education of junior developers.

HSBC GFX (Dec 2016 - Sept 2017) | DIGITAL TRANSFORMATION SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

My team of 6 delivered a suite of microservices in Clojure and ES6 and patched them into a legacy Java 6 / dojo.js monolith.

We worked from within the modernising, agile-embracing, daily-delivering, foriegn-exchange department of the investment bank, to bring their products into HSBCnet, one of the world's most used commercial payment applications, developed on a quarterly release cycle, with manual testing, and old SDLCs - straddling the politics of the 2 worlds.

Makers Academy (May 2016 - Sept 2017) | SOFTWARE ENGINEERING CONSULTANT

I was involved from the beginning in Makers Academy's Consultancy arm. I had a remit to work on Makers' education-based platform (Ruby on Rails) when not with a corporate partner (HSBC, Tek Systems, & Allegis Group). True to the MA spirit, I also completed the Makers Academy course - a bootcamp focusing on professional programming best practices (Agile, TDD, BDD, Pair Programming and the philosphies of Sandi Metz, Robert C Martin & Fred George).

Bob & Co (Nov 2014 - May 2016) | HEAD OF DIGITAL AND COMMUNICATIONS

A small media (film, TV, theatre) developer, and financier. I ran the technological, research & communication efforts. I also built (and maintained) the company website (single-handed), and other applications (Java & JS) for their partners & subsidiaries.

I later became Acting Director of Operations during a staff maternity leave, tasked with extensive audit and efficiency efforts in the IT, telecoms, and other office admin budgets.

SUMS Film & Media (Aug 2015 - Dec 2015) | DIGITAL & TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT

An independent film producer. I directly advised the Cheif Executive on their projects' digital strategies (see IMDB \leftarrow I'm three clicks from Tom Cruise). I worked on various applications, including marketing websites (*PHP*).

North Square Blue Oak (Jan 2014 - Mar 2014) | SABBATICAL ANALYST

A brokerage and corporate finance boutique, assessing new corporate finance opportunities in the digital sectors. The company drew heavily on my technological expertise in assessing potential investments.

CQS Asset Management (Feb 2013 - Mar 2013) | *MARGINS DEPT ANALYST & DEVELOPMENT INTERN*A \$13bn credit hedge fund: in liability management analysis with collateral specialists (creating an app to ass

A \$13bn credit hedge fund: in liability management analysis with collateral specialists (creating an app to assess marginal risks); and also with the strategic IT team, developing a credit price monitoring application (C#).

Office of the Digital & Cultural Minister (Nov 2008 - Nov 2014) | SENIOR PARLIAMENTARY ADVISOR I managed the Parliamentary Office of Rt. Hon. Ed Vaizey MP from the date of his Ministerial appointment. I oversaw the running of the office, interviewing, training and managing all junior staff. I worked on campaigns such as improving Wifi provision in public libraries and bringing coding into the national curriculum.

Aside from working on digital & media policy, I was given a wide remit and free-reign within the office, so I often programmed solutions to office problems, developing wordpress applications (*PHP*) for websites and databasing needs, and MS Access applications for automating emails and training.

Education

Physics 2:1 (BSc & ARCS): Imperial College London (Oct 2005 - July 2008)

I focussed on computational simulations, astrophysics, plasma physics, and the practicalities of nuclear fusion energy as a future energy source.

Final Year Degree Project (C++)

I received 93% for an computer simulation investigation into the process of evolution. I wrote the program from scratch, modelling biological systems. I was praised particularly for analysing great amounts of data, spotting patterns and anomalies, presenting them accessibly and quantifying the results in a manner that the department had never seen before.

Other Interests

CACIN - The Political Creative Industries Network (2008 - 2017) | DIRECTOR

I developed and maintained relationships with many key players in the tech & creative sectors on behalf Damian Collins MP, the Rt Hon Minister Ed Vaizey MP, and the Conservative Party HQ. I ran regular panels, drinks receptions and conferences across the UK, focusing on issues from the digital single market to diversity in the media.

The Digital Bazaar, Tate South Lambeth Library (2009 - 2013) | FOUNDING VOLUNTEER & IT EXPERT Taught basic computer, smartphone and other technology use to struggling members of the Lambeth community (many of whom did not have English as a first language). Runners-up for the CILIP Libraries Change Lives Award 2012.

Music - I have an intensely musical education. A music scholarship took me through secondary school. I sang in Christ Church Cathedral Choir, Oxford (we sang the credits to Blackadder and Vicar of Dibley; we performed in front of HM the queen; and we toured the USA, Japan, Germany, France, and Brazil). I also played the Saxophone, Violin, Piano, and guitar.

Cooking - I love cooking and spend a great deal of time in the kitchen. I have been paid to cook at events. And my recipes are popular on Instagram.

Tennis - I play regularly with a variety of partners and am coached professionally.